Elisabeth Telling Papers, 1902-1965
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Elisabeth Telling papers
1902-1965
Telling, Elisabeth, 1882-1979
MS 160
9 boxes (3.5 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Artist, Traveler, Ethnographer. The Elisabeth Telling Papers include extensive correspondence (1902-36) with her family describing her travels; diaries (1902-65); photographs and slides; writings; and her artwork. Her writings include published articles and her unpublished manuscript, "An Artist In Guatemala." Notable correspondents include playwright Stuart Walker, Sophia Smith Collection Director Margaret Storrs Grierson, sculptor Alice Morgan Wright, and artist Robert Eskridge.
Biographical Note
Elisabeth Telling was born in Milwaukee, Wisconsin in 1892. She graduated from Smith College in 1904 and studied at the Chicago Academy of Fine Arts from 1904 to 1905. Telling was a member of the Society of Women Geographers and traveled extensively in Europe, Central America, the Far East, Southeast Asia, Peru, and Haiti. She specialized in portraits of children and people in their native costume. Her artwork has been exhibited across the country and she published several articles about her travels.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Elisabeth Telling Papers include extensive correspondence (1902-36) with her family describing her travels; diaries (1902-65); photographs and slides; writings; and her artwork. Her writings include published articles and her unpublished manuscript, "An Artist In Guatemala." Notable correspondents include playwright Stuart Walker, Sophia Smith Collection Director Margaret Storrs Grierson, sculptor Alice Morgan Wright, and artist Robert Eskridge.
Organization of the Collection
This collection is organized into four series:
I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS
II. WRITINGS AND ARTWORK
III. CORRESPONDENCE
IV. SLIDES
OVERSIZED MATERIALS
Arrangement of the Collection
NOTE: This collection has not been fully processed; therefore:
The container list may not be completely accurate.
Although some materials may not be arranged in a logical order, please do not rearrange items or folders.
Locations of materials are subject to change when the collection is fully processed at a later date.
Some fragile items may not be protected in proper archival enclosures and should be handled with extreme care.
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without any additional restrictions.
History of the Collection
Elisabeth Telling donated her papers to the Sophia Smith Collection in 1980. Additional papers were transferred from the Smith College Archives in 1981.
Search Terms
Central America--Description and travel--Sources; East Asia--Description and travel--Sources; Europe--Description and travel--Sources; Indonesia--Description and travel--Sources; Peru--Description and travel--Sources; Voyages and travels--1900-1950--Sources; Ethnology--History--Sources; Women painters--United States--20th century--Sources; Telling, Elisabeth, 1882-1979; Eskridge, Robert Lee, b. 1891--Correspondence; Grierson, Margaret Storrs--Correspondence; Walker, Stuart, d. 1941--Correspondence; Wright, Alice Morgan--Correspondence
Additional Information
Related Material
There is additional material relating to Elisabeth Telling in the Smith College Archives Student files.
Contents List
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS
  - Contents (Box 1)
  - Biographical material (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Photographs, [see also SERIES IV. SLIDES]
    - General (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Travel (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Diaries, 1902-53 (Box 2)
  - Diaries, 1954-65 (Box 3)
- SERIES II. WRITINGS AND ARTWORK
  - Writings
    - "An Artist in Guatemala": manuscript, n.d. (1934?) (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - "Book on Guatemala": manuscript, early 1930s (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Untitled manuscript and notes, 1939, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, 1936-38 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Artwork, [see also OVERSIZE MATERIALS]
    - General (Box 4)
      - Portraits: exhibitions and miscellaneous (Box 4, Folder 8-9)
      - Illustrations (Box 4, Folder 10)
      - Correspondence (Box 4)
        - A-Z (Box 4, Folder 11)
        - Print Makers Society of California, 1921-27, [see also OVERSIZE MATERIALS] (Box 4, Folder 12)
        - Pine Mt. Settlement School, 1920-21 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Portraits, [see also OVERSIZE MATERIALS] (Box 4)
      - A-F (Box 5, Folder 13a)
      - G-L (Box 5, Folder 13b)
      - M-P (Box 5, Folder 13c)
      - R-Z (Box 5, Folder 13d)
      - Unidentified (Box 5)
        - Women (Box 5, Folder 13e)
        - Men (Box 5, Folder 13f)
        - Children (Box 5, Folder 13g)
      - Travel portraits (Box 5)
        - Bali, China, Ecuador (Box 5, Folder 13h)
        - Guatemala (Box 5, Folder 13i)
        - Japan, Java (Box 5, Folder 13j)
        - Peru, Siam (Box 5, Folder 13k)
        - Yucatan (Box 5, Folder 13l)
        - Unidentified (Box 5, Folder 13m)
    - Miscellaneous works (Box 5, Folder 13n)
    - Sketches, pencil (Box 5, Folder 13o)
    - Sketchbooks (8) (Box 6)
- SERIES III. CORRESPONDENCE
  - To family
    - France and Germany, 1902-14 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Germany, 1914-20 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - 1928 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - China, Java, 1930-31 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Bali, 1931 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Singapore, Bangkok, Bali, 1932 (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - Mexico, Guatemala, 1933-34 (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - Guatemala, 1935-36 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - To friends and associates, 1933-34, 1937 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - From family, 1914-20 (Box 8, Folder 23-24)
  - From friends and associates
    - Robert Eskridge, 1923-24 (Box 8, Folder 25)
    - Margaret Grierson, 1963-65 (Box 8, Folder 26)
    - Else Hall, from Germany, 1914-16 (Box 8, Folder 27)
    - Stuart A. Walker, 1917 (Box 8, Folder 28)
    - Louise H. Wood (AFSC), 1946 (Box 8, Folder 29)
    - Alice Morgan Wright, 1913-14 (Box 8, Folder 30)
- SERIES IV. SLIDES, [see also SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS-Photographs]
  - Peru, Haiti and Ecuador (Box 9)
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS
  - Color portraits (Map-case Flat File)
  - Color landscapes, flowers (Map-case Flat File)
  - Pencil sketches (Map-case Flat File)